Sky gatherers
The Minang people live on the shores of Lake Maninjao.
The Minang women work the rice paddies.
The men tend the coconut trees.
In Minang country, the coconut is
the main resource, with 3 million trees.
The men of the Coteaux clan
live off the riches of this forest.
They are the harvesters.
But they haven't climbed trees for a long time.
They found an ideal partner in nature:
the monkey.
Bourane had monkeys all his life.
In the Koto clan,
he is considered a master.
But today Bourane is retired,
there are no more monkeys.
He advises young trainers.
Bourane is old and tired.
Too tired to live with a monkey.
At least, that's what he believed.
Rayna is Bourane's wife.
And today, she receives an inheritance from an old aunt.
Jewelry, some furniture, and a monkey.
Among the Minang people, everything belongs to the women.
The house, the land, everything!
For Bourane, the interesting part of the inheritance
is a macaque monkey.
She is two and a half years old.
Her name is Bobo.
Bourane quickly learned to recognize the animal's qualities.
Its fur is dense.
Bobo can withstand ant attacks.
His cowlick is perfectly centered at the top of his head.
It's a sign of willpower.
The shape of his muscles suggests great endurance.
Bourane and Rayna had eight children.
They are grown now.
They've all gone to the city
but without them, the house is quiet.
Every breeder has their own method.
Bourane always wanted his monkeys to participate.
to family life.
He receives them at his table.
and gives them a niche in the house.
Bobo is scared; he doesn't know this house.
Bourane has already lived there with about twenty monkeys.
He knows that he needs to show them affection
to capture their attention.
This is his way of making himself heard.
Since her children left home,
Rayna has wanted a quiet life.
His rice paddies give him plenty of work.
Rayna thought it through carefully.
She needs a buffalo to help her in her rice paddies.
Bobo will be sold.
With the money, she will buy a buffalo.
Among the Minang people, women make the decisions.
Among the Minang, it's official.
Bourane's wife asked him to test
Bobo to determine its value.
Here, a well-trained monkey is worth the price of a buffalo.
Bobo can't do anything.
She doesn't understand orders.
She can't manage to pick the coconuts.
A large gathering competition takes place every year.
The young trainers prepare their monkeys.
It takes place in two weeks.
Usually, Bourane always wins it.
But this year, the youngsters are reassured.
Bobo isn't going to worry them.
Bobo is absolutely worthless.
Rayna won't get a penny out of him.
And for her, this is very bad news.
Like all monkeys, Bobo is possessive,
jealous, and she wants to be the center of attention.
family attention.
But Rayna doesn't want to get attached to Bobo.
Rayna asked her husband to make Bobo
a good picker.
The old master starts the training of Bobo from scratch.
Bourane says it takes several months
to train a monkey.
But Bobo is very talented.
She understood everything in just a few days.
He just needs a little more training.
When the day is over,
Bourane chooses a ripe walnut for Bobo.
But with a monkey, learning through reward is not enough.
The monkey needs to feel protected and pampered.
Bourane has become indispensable.
Bobo would like to see her all to herself,
all the time.
Copra is the flesh of the coconut.
It is ground, pressed and cooked for hours.
Oil is extracted from it
and sold at the market.
Milk is used as an ingredient in cooking
and as food for babies.
Rayna will go sell the produce
from the first Bobo harvests.
Every morning, Bourane practices his Silat.
He pays homage to his land.
Lake Maninjao has formed its bed
in the craters of three volcanoes.
Its shores and islands belong to the clan of Buran,
the Kotos.
The nut pickers are always on the move.
They go from one person's house to another's, as needed.
Out of ten nuts picked by Bobo, Bourane takes one for himself.
The other nine belong to the owner of the tree.
For bobo, foraging holds no more secrets.
Soon, she will make it rain from the sky
500 to 1000 nuts a day, like her elders.
Buran has a secret garden.
Somewhere on the foothills of the crater
A torrent of hot water flows.
The old man is greeted by the guardians of the place,
the Siamangs, the howler gibbons.
A fleeting miracle.
The Rafflesia, the largest flower in the world.
It only lives for three days.
For three days, hundreds of bees will come to forage on his hectare
and lose oneself in its petals.
Because the Rafflesia is carnivorous.
Its nectar is poisonous.
After a long day of gathering,
the monkey's muscles are tense.
Bobo is still developing.
She won't be fully grown until she's three years old.
Bourane is keeping a close eye on its growth.
Bobo accepted his new father
and Bourane rediscovered his passion for the profession.
However, we will have to part ways.
In Balimbing, they brought out the Minang colors:
yellow for nobility, red for cheerfulness,
black for bravery.
The day of the big competition has arrived.
Now is the time for Bobo to prove himself
in the eyes of the clan.
Bourane wants her to win.
He's been motivating her for a week.
His reputation is at stake.
For Rayna, this competition will primarily
determine the value of her monkey.
Bobo managed to pick 7 nuts in 2 minutes.
Born in Assyria.
Sahar is a wealthy merchant.
He was the one who refereed the competition.
And now he wants to hurt himself.
The negotiations are secret;
no one is to know the amount.
Bourane doesn't have the heart to part with Bobo.
But among the Minangs,
Nothing is decided without the agreement of women.
Women preserve the heritage.
Neither the house nor the land,
Neither the jewelry nor the jewelry can be sold.
Now Rayna will be able to buy her buffalo.
The market takes place in Lumbu Bassum every Saturday.
That's where copra is sold and
that we buy the animals.
Rayna thought it through carefully.
Even though she struggles in the rice paddies,
Even though a buffalo would have been a great relief,
she decided to buy Bobo back.
Bourane and Bobo are going to pick some more coconuts together.
Rayna will wait for another opportunity
to get her buffalo.
After all, Bobo provides them with what they need to live.
And besides, we mustn't separate
the sky gatherers.